To pray is to open your heart to God, to lift your heart and mind to the Father, to partner
with Jesus, to bend the arc of human history in the direction of the Kingdom.
To pray is to do something with the Spirit, and for the Spirit to do something in us.
To speak and to listen.
To pray is to commune with a God who is closer to us than we are to ourselves.
Well, good morning, Canvas Community Church.
For those of you that haven't met me yet, my name is Ryan.
I have the privilege of being one of the pastors here.
So grateful for that time of worship and that invitation to acknowledge God's presence
in this place.
All of the Bible is about the fact that the God who created the universe desires us to
be in His presence.
He created us for relationship with Him.
And ever since the beginning, the story goes, we've been rebelling and choosing other things
to find pleasure and satisfaction in.
And if you're anything like me, you've probably tried a lot of things and many things have fallen
short.
And so, man, we're in this new series called Practicing the Way, which really is about habits
that allow us to be in the presence of God.
We've been spending four weeks on prayer, and it's really a practice-based discipleship.
It's intentional, it's aimed at spending time in the presence of God.
And the American church, and even just post-enlightenment, I feel like has maybe overvalued intellectual
discipleship and to the detriment of relational-based discipleship.
And so throughout the time, throughout the next three years, really, we're going to look
at nine practices from the life and teachings of Jesus, aimed at helping us get into the
presence of God.
And I just want to be super clear here that, like, this is not some legalistic type of thing
that, like, you check the right boxes, you put in the right equation, and then God rewards
you.
The practices really are just aimed at you spending time with God.
And for any of us that have spent any time in the presence of God, we know that that is
where transformation happens.
I love how John Mark Homer puts it.
He says, practices can't transform me into a person of Christ-like character.
These habits, these practices, these things we're inviting you to participate in, they can't
do anything to transform you into a person of Christ-like character.
All they can do is open up a deeper part of yourself to the power and presence of God.
The power and presence of God does the transformative work in our hearts and our minds.
So that's our goal, is to spend time in the presence of God and allow the Holy Spirit to
transform our hearts and our minds.
So far, we've talked about prayer as talking to God.
We've talked about quoting liturgy, praying the Scriptures, talked about the Lord's Prayer
and using the Lord's Prayer as a model for how we pray to God.
We've talked about talking with God, through praise, through lament, which we're not often
good at, right?
We hide our anger from God.
We withdraw from God when we're angry.
But God is not scared of our anger.
He's not scared of our frustration and our pain.
We talk to God through praise, lament, petition, and intercession.
We ask for what we need and for what others need.
Last week, Sean talked about listening, quieting ourselves before God, allowing God to speak
to us.
And today, we will just talk about being with God, being in the presence of God.
There's actually certain sects of Orthodox Jews that don't allow this praise, lament, petition
type prayer on the Sabbath because it feels too much like work, like we're laboring with
God to try and get something done, to see something accomplished.
And so there's this type of prayer that just allows ourselves to acknowledge God's presence
and be with him.
No agenda.
Giving him space to do what he can only do.
So that's kind of our goal for this morning.
Sound like a plan?
Okay, let me pray and then we'll hop in.
Father, we acknowledge your presence in this place.
We know that your Holy Spirit is here and we expect him to do what only he can do.
God, prepare our minds and our hearts to hear from you, to receive something from you, and
to accept your invitation into a deeper walk with you.
God, everything this world has to offer falls short.
Everything our culture is going to celebrate tonight in the Super Bowl is fine and good,
but it all falls short.
It's all worshiping something less than what we were created to worship.
And so as we consume content with our culture today, may we see it for what it is.
It's a game that you've given us that we can enjoy.
But at the end of the day, if we put our stock, our worship, and what this world has to offer,
we will come up short.
So today, Father, may we acknowledge your presence in deeper ways.
May we accept your invitation.
God, may we draw near to you and may you draw near to us.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
If you want to follow along with me in your Bible, I'm going to be in Psalm 46 throughout
the time.
I'm also just going to quote a lot of Scripture today.
Does that sound like a good plan to people?
Okay, good.
Yes, always.
And just as a disclaimer, I've had a question or two from people throughout the past week
or two about specifically this topic that we're going to be talking about today, contemplative
prayer, and about whether or not it's biblical.
And I think that it is.
And I'm going to quote a lot of Scripture to try and prove it.
I just want to let anybody know that if you're struggling or wrestling with any of the concepts
that are shared from stage, I, our elder board, our governance board, we'd love to chat with
you and wrestle with you about what the Scriptures say.
And that iron would sharpen iron, that we would become more like Christ together.
So that's just a disclaimer up front.
I'm not going to make you raise your hands this week because it's a little heavy.
Sometimes I make you raise your hands, but I don't want to embarrass you.
But hypothetically speaking, if I were to ask if anybody in the room is feeling anxious,
stressed out, or overwhelmed, would any of us be brave enough to raise our hands, right?
Let me give a couple of examples of some things that might be stressing us out.
Any rejection of close relationships, any relational tension that any of you are dealing with.
Again, I won't make you raise your hand, but just think.
Is there any relational tension, any familial relationships that have been severed that is weighing on you?
Any stress from your career, success, aspirations, anybody got imposter syndrome in their job,
or even just as being an adult?
Anybody feel like you're just pretending and hoping nobody knows?
Anybody in here lost a loved one recently?
Anybody in here fear being punished for standing up for what's right?
Some of us who work in secular environments,
we might feel like there are certain things that we just can't go along with.
And if we don't go along with those things,
we might not be able to get where we want to go in our career.
Or just the busyness of seemingly unending daily to-do lists.
Any moms in the room get to the end of the day
and realize that you didn't eat anything all day this week?
Anybody brave enough?
Like, we're going to talk about fasting over the next couple weeks.
Some of the moms in the room are like,
I do that on accident sometimes.
How about all of the above converging into one overly stressed out moment of life?
Well, believe it or not,
these are the exact circumstances that Jesus and his disciples are facing all at the same time.
In the book of Mark, chapter 6,
the disciples have dealt with all of this stuff going on.
Jesus is rejected in his hometown of Nazareth.
His family and his friends push him out of town,
threatening to stone him and kill him.
John the Baptist's cousin and close friend gets his head chopped off by Roman authorities.
The disciples go out two by two and they have incredible success.
They're healing people.
They're casting out demons.
They're having all of this success and they're dealing with all of the emotional waves
of what God is doing in and through them.
Maybe pressure to take credit for some of that.
And then there's just so many crowds gathering around them.
It says that they didn't even have time to eat.
And it's in that context that my slides are a little ahead,
so it might be giving it away to you a little bit.
But it's in that context that the God of the universe doesn't make the sun stand still,
which he's done in the past and could do if he wanted to, right?
Give us a few extra hours in the day, a little bit more time.
He doesn't raise John the Baptist from the dead,
which we know he has the power to do.
He doesn't crush his enemies or flip tables over this time.
He doesn't even recruit more disciples to make the load a little bit easier on the ones that he has.
What does he do?
He says this in Mark chapter 6.
After all of the stress and anxiety and tension and emotional trauma of a difficult season in ministry,
he says come away by yourselves to a lonely place and rest a while.
Come away with me by yourselves to a lonely place and we'll rest a while.
In the midst of what has been one of the most difficult, emotionally draining seasons of the disciples' life,
Jesus' invitation.
Anybody brave enough to say that with me?
And yet here's the deal.
There's saints in here who have been following Jesus for a long time,
who have walked through some of the darkest seasons that any of us could ever imagine.
And if I gave them the opportunity to come up here and testify,
they would say that God's presence is all they needed in the midst of that difficult challenge.
See, we live in a cultural moment that's busier than ever.
Technology was supposed to make our lives more efficient,
which was supposed to give us more free time,
which we were supposed to use to rest, relax, invest in important relationships,
you know, be good humans.
But what did we do instead?
We took the efficiency and we made ourselves more busy.
We invested ourselves in more things and we are over busy and hurried like crazy.
And even if your personal life is going pretty good,
you add unnecessary stress and anxiety and worry to your life
by doing what I call the death scroll, right?
You're filling your mind and your heart with the burdens and stresses and anxieties
of people that you don't even know.
And in the midst of all of this stress and worry and anxiety and hurry,
Christ's invitation to you, I believe, is the same as his invitation to his disciples
when they found themselves stressed, overwhelmed, anxious, hurried.
Come away to a lonely place.
Be with me.
Rest in my presence.
So this is what we're talking about this morning.
This type of prayer that's aimed at resting in God's presence,
inviting God's presence into your life,
and just relaxing into the grace of God.
Without words at times.
And throughout history, it's been called different things at different times.
In the presence of God, who made you, loves you.
And listen to this.
He is sovereign over all of your fear, anxiety, and worry.
You cannot add an extra moment to your life by worrying.
So what if we just took God's invitation to heart and we just got away for a few minutes?
And I know how hard this sounds.
Believe me.
I've tried it the past couple of weeks.
And with 10 months old, it's difficult.
It's challenging.
But what if we just got five minutes a day to just get away and rest in the presence of God?
Psalm chapter 91, verses 1 through 10 says this.
Those who live in the shelter of the Most High will find rest in the shadow of the Almighty.
Does that sound good to anybody this morning?
This I declare about the Lord.
He alone is my refuge, my place of...
I declare about the Lord.
He alone is my refuge, my place of safety.
He is my God, and I trust Him.
For He will rescue you from every trap and protect you from every deadly disease.
We should have read that in 2020 a bit more.
He will cover you with His feathers.
This intimate, relational picture of a mother hen embracing her chicks under her wings.
He will shelter you with His wings.
His faithful promises are your armor and your protection.
Do not be afraid of the terrors of the night nor the arrow that flies in the day.
Do not dread the disease that stalks in darkness, nor the disaster that strikes at midday.
Though a thousand fall at your side, though ten thousand are dying around you,
these evils will not touch you.
Listen to this.
Just open your eyes.
Acknowledge God's presence, His sovereignty over all of your stress, worry, and anxiety,
and see how the wicked are punished.
If you make the Lord your refuge,
if you make the Most High your shelter,
no evil will conquer you.
So I've been thinking about contemplative prayer a lot the past couple of weeks.
Different people talk about it in different ways,
and some people seem to kind of indicate that this is,
that it takes a level of spiritual maturity to get to a point where you can kind of just rest in God's presence.
And I don't know that I fully agree with that,
because as I was studying and thinking about this,
I got to observe my baby with my wife.
And Rory has not the maturity to talk,
nor the maturity to listen.
But I tell you what,
when that kid gets in between a rock and a hard place,
he throws himself into the presence of his mother.
He knows where to go when stress, anxiety, fear, difficulty face his life.
And I think there's something that has to do with what Jesus said,
that we need a childlike faith.
That some of us, we've matured so far beyond that.
We're so smart.
We know so many passages of Scripture.
We can quote so many things.
We've got our systematic theology just rooted down.
We're too mature to throw ourselves into the presence of God.
And I just can't help but think that today,
God is extending to all of us an invitation.
Not a legalistic requirement.
Not a religious thing that you have to check the right box.
You have to do it for the right amount of time,
the right amount of days a week.
It's an invitation to throw yourself into the presence of God.
So, how do we develop a rhythm of prayer
that allows us to rest in God's presence?
I've got four steps we're going to cover for the rest of our time.
I couldn't make them spell anything.
I really tried.
I'm sorry.
I know, if I was a good pastor, I would have figured it out.
But pause, number one, pause.
Number two, surrender.
Number three, contemplate.
And number four, receive.
This is not a silver bullet to euphoria.
This is not, if you do the right things in the right order,
everything is perfect.
This is just four steps that I think,
if we regularly enter into the presence of God with these four steps,
if we're able to pause, surrender, contemplate, and receive,
I think that God will show up and give us genuine rest.
So, number one, pause.
Psalm 46, verses 10 and 11.
Be still and know that I am God.
I will be honored by every nation.
I will be honored throughout the world.
Be still and know that the creator of the universe is still on the throne
and that he's sovereign over all of your problems and your worries and your anxieties.
The first step to contemplative prayer is just to pause.
Find a quiet and comfortable place that you can get alone
and take a few big, deep breaths.
People get weird about this.
It's just science.
It's good for your body to breathe from your diaphragm.
Most of us are so stressed, worried, anxious, hurried,
that we never get belly breaths in.
Okay, there's nothing weird about this.
It's just breathe the way God created you to breathe.
All right, let's do that.
Let's relax a little bit.
Pause.
No phones.
No distractions.
I'm just going to get real vulnerable with you.
Even if my phone's in the other room and I hear it vibrate, I'm gone.
Like, it's over.
My pausing is done.
And so find something.
Do not disturb.
Whatever it is.
And find a comfortable place.
There's different places for different people.
Favorite chair, porch swing, garden.
I grew up with a dad that fished a lot.
And he would say at times, sometimes I feel closer to God on the water
than I do in the sanctuary of a church.
Anybody?
Find that place for you to relax and to pause.
And if you're a mother of young children,
maybe you just have to pretend like you're going to the bathroom
for a bit longer than normal.
Maybe you pull your car into the driveway,
or before you get to the driveway, you pull into somebody else's driveway.
And you just like 10 minutes in the car and let your husband not know
that you're done with whatever chore or errand you were doing.
Just close your eyes.
Take a few deep breaths and acknowledge God's presence in your life.
See, most of us, many of us, I won't say most of us,
I'll throw myself under the bus here,
even mature disciples of Jesus,
we often live as functional atheists.
We don't acknowledge God's presence in our every moment lives.
We get stressed and overwhelmed.
Our eyes, we're Peter, stepping out to the water,
and then everything else distracts us away from the presence of God.
And so this moment to pause is just a moment to acknowledge
the thing that's always been true.
God is present with you.
But how often do we live as if he's not?
I love what Peter Greig says.
He says, it's not that God's not present to you,
it's that you are absent to God.
And this time of pausing and just acknowledging God's presence
is a moment for us to reflect on something that's always been true,
but we have oftentimes been living as if it isn't.
So we pause.
We acknowledge God's presence.
I love how Hebrews chapter 10 puts it.
This is so powerful.
Don't miss this.
So, dear brothers and sisters,
we can boldly enter heaven's most holy place
because of the blood of Jesus.
We enter God's presence because of what Jesus has done for us.
By his death, Jesus opened a new and life-giving way
through the curtain into the most holy place.
And since we have a great high priest who rules over God's house,
let us go right into the presence of God
with sincere hearts, fully trusting him.
For our guilty conscience has been sprinkled with Christ's blood
to make us clean,
and our bodies have been washed with pure water.
No matter where you are in your life,
no matter what patterns and habitual sins
that you are struggling with,
you have confident, bold access into the presence of God.
God created you for that type of presence.
He's invited you into that presence.
And the author of Hebrews here mentions the old way,
that just the Levite priest once a year
would have the opportunity to enter into the presence of God.
But because of Jesus' blood, his death, burial, and resurrection,
you and I have bold confidence to enter the presence of God
as children of God.
I remember when I was,
for a while,
college and some other years,
I had a on and off addiction to pornography, right?
And I remember when I would fail,
when I would fall short,
it was like I needed three or four days away from God
to like make myself feel like I was clean enough
to maybe come back into his presence.
And I don't know what you're dealing with in your life,
but I can't help but think there are some of you here
who are in patterns of sin,
and you think that that sin
is causing this disconnect between you and God,
that you can't confidently enter his presence.
And I'm just here to tell you this morning,
we are all woefully sinful.
Our hearts are deceitful and wicked.
And we all, right now, today,
no matter what we've done,
have boldness to enter the presence of God
because of what Jesus has done.
Do not neglect Christ's sacrifice
by refusing to receive the forgiveness
that he's freely given to you.
With boldness, enter God's presence
day in and day out.
How often do we actually enter God's presence
with this boldness and acknowledge it?
Honestly, this is the hardest step of the process.
Getting time to pause, right?
The other three steps, if you have time to pause,
if you get away for a few minutes,
get the phone off,
somebody else is taking care of the kids,
the other three steps are pretty easy,
but the enemy wants nothing more
than to keep you from getting to the first step.
Yeah.
Dallas Willard, Christian philosopher,
was once asked,
what's the greatest enemy to spiritual health
in our culture?
He paused for a minute and he responded,
ruthlessly eliminate hurry from your life.
Hurry is the great enemy of the spiritual life.
Any of us uncomfortable with silence?
Silence.
See, most of us,
when we get alone by ourselves,
we will be distracted.
We will be overwhelmed by thoughts
and feelings and distractions.
We'll be uncomfortable just sitting in silence.
And I think it's because we do have this propensity
to fill our lives with busy and hurry.
We avoid any silence at all
because we're afraid of what we might think
or feel or hear from the Lord.
And I just,
I think we've got to get over that.
I think we've got to plunge into the scariness
of the silence.
Be alone with ourselves and with God
and allow him to do the work
that only he can do
when we eliminate the hurry and the distractions.
See, Adam and Eve,
after the fall,
God did what God did.
He walked in the garden in the cool of night
wanting to be with Adam and Eve.
They got busy making clothes,
blaming each other and hiding.
From that point on,
I believe one of humanity's tactics,
one of our fleshly tactics
to avoid God's presence
is busyness and hurry.
And Jesus is inviting us to pause
and to acknowledge his presence.
And if you're anything like me
and you're just successful at this,
immediately.
Distraction, distraction, distraction.
What's for dinner?
Who's picking up the kid?
Did I pay that bill?
Is there enough money
getting put into my Roth IRA account?
Do I have enough life insurance
to cover if something bad happens?
These are mine.
I don't know what yours are,
but there you go.
Now you know.
Right?
Pause.
Step two is surrender.
As these anxious thoughts
fill your mind and your heart,
we lay them at the feet of Jesus.
Let's read the rest of Psalm 46.
Starting in verse one,
God is our refuge and our strength,
always ready to help
in times of trouble.
So we will not fear
when earthquakes come
and when mountains crumble
into the sea.
Let the oceans roar and foam.
Let the mountains tremble
as the waters surge.
A river brings joy
to the city of God,
the sacred home
of the Most High.
God dwells in that city.
It cannot be destroyed.
From the very break of day,
God will protect it.
The nations are in chaos
and their kingdoms crumble.
God's voice thunders
and the earth melts.
The Lord of heaven's army
is here among us.
The God of Israel
is our fortress.
Come,
see the glorious works
of the Lord.
See how he brings destruction
upon the world.
He causes wars to end
throughout the earth.
He breaks the bow
and snaps the spear
and he burns the shields
with fire.
I can't help but see
the authors of this psalm
confidently laying out
biblical truth
about God's sovereignty,
his power,
and his strength
and then getting distracted.
Earthquakes,
mountains crumble,
oceans roar,
but God is like a river
running through the sea, right?
Nations are in chaos.
Kingdoms are at war.
Is this how anybody else's
prayer life is like?
And so I can't help but see them
just offering
these distractions,
these worries.
Legitimate worries.
Earthquakes,
that's a legitimate worry,
especially when you live
out in the middle of nowhere
with no protection, right?
Wars, famine,
all of these things
are legitimate worries.
But they keep coming back
to God's presence.
They keep reminding themselves
of what they know to be true
even though they're caused
to be distracted.
This psalm is littered
with confident faith
in the promises of God
mixed with distractions
and acknowledgement
of external circumstances.
And if you get away
to a lonely place
to pause to be with God,
your mind and your heart
will be filled with distractions,
worries, anxieties, and fears.
And it's just,
I'm giving you this invitation.
Just lay them
at the feet of Jesus.
Don't try and ignore them.
Don't try and pretend
like they're not there.
Just bring them to God.
Yes, God,
I am worried about
if my Roth IRA
has enough money,
but I believe
that you are a provider,
that you care,
that you're sovereign.
I'm not going to worry
about that right now.
I'm going to trust you.
I heard a quote
the past week
that said,
stress is taking ownership
over something
that you don't have
authority over.
How many of us
come into prayer
and our minds
are filled with things
that we think
are under our control
and reality,
it's all things
that God is sovereign over
and God's inviting us
to surrender
those things to Him.
So what things
are outside of your authority?
What things
are you taking ownership of?
Surrender it to God
intentionally
and enter His presence
even just for a few moments.
Actively acknowledging
everything in your mind
and your heart,
not hiding from it,
not burying it,
bringing it to God.
And here's the cool thing
about this stage.
Surrender is going to repeat
through the rest
of the stages
because you're going to get
to the time
where you're contemplating
all the things of God
and guess what's going to happen?
The distractions
that you surrendered yourself to
like 30 seconds ago
are going to come back.
And then,
then you're going to feel defeated.
Then you're going to feel discouraged.
Then you're going to feel like
I'm a failure.
I can't pray.
And guess what?
Don't feel that way.
I heard another quote.
I couldn't find the source
for this one.
I really wanted to find it
because it's great.
They said,
don't view constant distractions
in prayer
as discouragement
but as a perpetual invitation
to re-surrender your mind
and your heart to God.
As you go along this process,
as worry and fear
keep coming back,
and even if you chase
the rabbit hole
for five or ten minutes
thinking about all the ways
in which you need
to do different things
to get rid of the stress,
when you snap back into it
and you realize
that you're being distracted,
bring it to God.
God,
I was just distracted
for five minutes
thinking about
if my Roth IRA account
has enough money.
and I know
that that's not something
that's worthy
of my distraction
so I'm bringing it
back to your feet.
You are sovereign
and in control.
I trust you.
All right?
So,
start by pausing,
creating space
to acknowledge God's presence,
surrender your anxious thoughts.
Now,
we contemplate.
We contemplate.
We think about God.
Now that our minds
and our hearts
are absence of distraction
as much as possible,
we focus our minds on God.
This is a great time
for Lectio Divina
if that's something
that works for you.
We think about
who God is to us
and who we are to God.
I love Psalm chapter one.
It says,
It's this time
of meditation,
thinking about,
thinking about the Scriptures.
This is why Bible reading,
regular Bible reading
is so important.
God's not going to bring
something to your mind
about himself
or about you
that isn't echoed
in the Scriptures.
It's important
for new believers
if you think
God's telling you something.
Bring it to the community.
Is this consistent
with Scripture?
So we think about God.
We meditate on God.
Think about his faithfulness.
We started a prayer rhythm
with the staff
this past week.
And I love telling you guys
how bad I am at stuff.
Is that all right?
I'm the king of starting
great things
and never finishing them.
So we did a prayer rhythm
this week.
I can't tell you
if it's going to happen
next week or not,
but we did it this week.
And Donovan,
he just shared
this testimony
from his life
years and years ago
the way that God showed up
and did a miraculous thing
in his life.
And all of us
were just crying.
I'm sure he would not
like me to tell you
that he cries,
but Ethan,
your dad cries.
It's great.
Think about the ways
in which God has shown up
and done immeasurably more
than you could ever ask,
think, or imagine.
Think about God's faithfulness.
Think about God's love for you.
Colossians 3, 2 says,
think about the things
of heaven,
not the things
of this earth.
You have so many opinions
in your mind
of what people think
about you,
of what you think
people think about you,
whether or not
it's actually true or not.
Think about what God
thinks about you
because that's,
at the end of the day,
all that matters.
Transition your thoughts
towards how God
thinks about you.
Far too often,
our view of what God
thinks of us
comes from this world
or the opinions
of others,
not God.
His love for you,
His patience towards you,
His kindness
is far more
than we ever
actually receive.
As we spend time
contemplating
and examining
our thoughts about God
and His thoughts
about us,
we slowly begin
to just rest
in His presence.
we tend to take on
what we think about
a lot, right?
We become
what we contemplate.
And so,
I heard a study
about Gen Z people.
No offense, guys.
I love you.
I really do.
I love you guys.
I'm right there with you.
But it talked about
like strong Christians
and the amount
of content
that they consume
that's Christian
versus non-Christian.
And it was
something crazy.
Like 2,000 hours
a year
is non-Christian
and like 200 hours
a year.
I don't have the stats
off the top of my head.
I wish I did.
But we become
like what we contemplate.
We all know this.
I am,
I'm the king
of like a three-hour
Pat McAfee sports podcast,
which is fine.
There's nothing wrong
with Pat McAfee,
but three hours
of Pat McAfee
and 20 minutes
with the Lord
and you wonder
why I said the F word
when I stubbed my toe
and,
right?
Shh,
don't tell anybody.
Is this,
turn the live stream off.
We know this.
How many of us
have friends
who all they do,
don't raise your hands.
I can feel it
coming already.
How many of us
have friends
who all they do
is watch Fox News?
How many of us
have friends
who all they do
is watch MSNBC?
Here's my question.
Are they nice?
Here's my other question.
Do you know
what they think
about every hot topic issue
that there is?
We know what they think
because they become
what they contemplate.
We become
what we contemplate.
And so,
man,
I'm inviting us,
I think the Lord's
inviting us
to take a look
at our balance.
How much time
are we spending
contemplating on,
we're going to spend
five hours
watching a football game
tonight.
It's fine.
I love football.
I got the red zone.
I watch more than
five hours of football
most Sundays,
right?
Like,
cut the live stream.
But what are we
thinking about?
What are we contemplating?
And how is it affecting
the way that we love
our neighbor as ourself?
Because that's the whole
point of this thing,
being in the presence
of God,
is that he would
conform us into a person
that's like Jesus.
John Mark Comer
shares the story
about a farmer
in a small town
who would come
to the church
and sit in the pew
for hours at a time.
And one day,
the priest came up
to him and said,
what is it that you
do here every day?
The farmer said,
I look at him,
he looks at me,
and we are happy.
I look at him,
he looks at me,
and we are happy.
This is the invitation
of God.
Come away with me.
Sit in my presence.
Think about
who I am to you
and who you are to me
and rest.
John,
the night of the Lord's Supper,
gives us this account
of him just reclining
back into the chest
of Jesus.
That's our invitation.
When we're stressed,
when we're worried,
when we're anxious,
when we're afraid,
we contemplate God
and we receive
his presence.
The end goal
of contemplative prayer
is that you would just
sit and receive
the loving presence
of God in your life
so that you might live
as a person of love
to those around you.
Again,
if you think you're
receiving the loving
presence of God
in your life
and you're a jerk
to everyone around you,
maybe you're sitting
with somebody
other than God.
This is the goal.
Not that we're perfect,
but that as we learn
to spend time
with a God
who loves us unconditionally,
even though we don't
deserve it,
the more we meditate
on him,
the more we realize
how much we are
unworthy of his grace
and yet he freely
extends it
and then we leave
that place
and those around us
do things
that don't deserve
our grace
and forgiveness
and guess what we do?
We extend it
to them anyway
because we've just
been in a room
receiving it
for ourselves.
We pour out
from a full cup.
It's about positioning
ourselves back
into the garden
naked and unashamed
before God
because,
this is back
to the Hebrews passage,
because of the blood
of Jesus,
we've been sprinkled
clean.
We literally
can sit before God
naked and unashamed
with all of our failures,
with all of our mistakes,
not trying to cover them up
or say,
I'll do better next time,
just Jesus loves me.
He forgives me.
He wants to be with me.
Matthew chapter 5,
no, 6, sorry.
Verse 5 says,
when you pray,
don't be like the hypocrites
who love to pray publicly
on street corners
and in the synagogues
where everyone can see them.
I tell you the truth,
that is all the reward
that they will get.
They get the reward
of being seen
as being holy
and righteous
and good.
But,
when you pray,
go away
by yourself.
shut the door behind you
and pray
to your Father
in private
and then your Father
who sees everything
will reward you.
And I don't know about you,
but I have often
filled my own theology
into that end passage.
And I say,
oh, well,
God will reward me
by answering my prayers,
right?
Does it say that?
I think we tend
to input our own ideas
back into the text.
We like to think
the reward is answered prayers,
but what if,
what if God's reward
for those of us
who get away,
pray in lonely places,
what if the reward
is just his presence?
Is that enough?
Would that be enough for you?
Would that be enough
for me?
I want to say yes.
And I can say
over the past few weeks
of trying to practice
this little by little
that the more time
I spend with God,
the more I realize
that everything
outside of that room
pales in comparison
to being in the presence
of God.
James 4.8,
it's a promise.
He says,
come close to God
and God will come close to you.
Wash your hands,
you sinners,
purify your hearts
for your loyalty
is divided between God
and the world.
Got to be honest
with where we're at,
perceive God's forgiveness
and his transforming power.
So I'd encourage you
to find a rhythm
of prayer
where you can pause
before God,
even if it's just
a few minutes,
even if it's not
every day a week
for a while,
like just start something.
Surrender your anxious thoughts
and your sinful behaviors.
This isn't a thing
where we like go in
proud of our sin
and our failures
and we're like,
well, God loves me anyway.
Right?
We repent.
We acknowledge our failures.
We ask for God's forgiveness
and we do go out
in the power
of the Holy Spirit
seeking to put sin to death.
But here's the deal.
The more sin you put to death,
this is something
that I'm learning,
this is fun,
the more sin you put to death
and then the more
you come back
into the presence of God,
you would think
you'd feel a little bit
better about yourself,
right?
The closer you get to God,
the more you realize
how sinful you are.
Even if you're putting
a ton of sin to death,
even if patterns of sin
are falling off your life,
gossip, slander,
lust, temptation,
addiction,
even if it's all going away,
when you sit
in the presence
of the holy,
just,
righteous,
forgiving God,
you realize
how far off the mark
you still are,
which gives us
more and more grace
for the people
who sin against us.
We become a people of love.
We pause,
we surrender,
we contemplate,
and we receive.
This is the overarching
narrative of the Bible.
Just as we think about,
I have,
I've read some articles
this past week
about people who
are opposed
to contemplative prayer
and I just,
the overarching narrative
of the Bible
is that God created you
to be with him.
Read Genesis,
God wants you
to be with him
and we've rejected
that plan,
we've sought to find
joy and satisfaction
apart from him
and it's like grasping
after the wind.
And God,
throughout the history
of the Bible,
starting with Adam and Eve
and the promise
to crush the serpent's head
from Abraham
through the nation of Israel
and culminating in Jesus,
God has always been
inviting his people
into his presence,
continually making us,
making a way for us
to be with him again.
That's the point
of the Bible.
of your faith in Jesus.
If your faith in Jesus
doesn't lead you
to want to be with God,
it's just a moral code.
It's a legalistic structure
that might make you
feel more righteous
than others,
but it's supposed
to be about being
with the God
who loves you
and who made you.
He's continually making a way
for us to be with him again,
culminating
in his ultimate expression
of love in Jesus.
Contemplative prayer
is a practice
aimed at getting us
back to the place
where he made us to be,
experiencing what John
in the Gospels
called the abundant life,
sitting before God,
naked and unashamed,
receiving his unconditional love
so that we can go out
and extend it to others.
All right,
so this message
has been primarily,
almost completely,
to those of us
who have already
trusted in Jesus.
And we try really hard
at Canvas.
I try really hard
to preach messages
that also engage
those of you
who are just kicking
the tires on Christianity.
You're considering
the claims of Jesus.
You're thinking about it.
Maybe you've got somebody
in your life
who's living radically
for Jesus
and you're just like,
this person's really weird,
but man,
I kind of want
what they have,
so I'm going to go
to their church
and see what's up.
If that's you,
I really try hard
to do something for you
and so here's
what I'm going to do.
In an effort
to land the plane
and to get everybody
in the room on board,
I'm going to go back
to my opening questions.
Are you stressed?
Anxious?
Worried?
I don't care
if you follow Jesus or not.
Are you stressed?
Anxious?
Worried?
Have you experienced
rejection
and relational tension?
Stress of career success,
aspirations,
imposter syndrome?
Have you lost a loved one?
Are you dealing
with the sorrow
and grief
and pain of this world?
Or the busyness
of a seemingly
unending daily to-do list?
Or I guess I could ask it
the way that Jesus asked it.
Are any of you tired
of carrying heavy burdens?
Jesus said
to a group of people
who were considering
his claims
that he was the Messiah,
the Son of God,
are any of you
tired
and carrying heavy burdens?
His response
was a simple invitation.
Come to me,
all you who are weary
and heavy laden,
and I will give you rest.
It's a soul level rest
that you're longing for
and you might not
even realize it.
Whether you've already
placed your faith
in Jesus or not,
I truly believe
Jesus is the one answer
to the overwhelming
stress and anxiety
that this world
has to offer.
I love how Eugene Peterson
summarized this text
in his own words.
He said,
are you tired,
worn out,
burn out on religion?
Come to me,
get away with me,
and you'll recover
your life.
I'll show you
how to take a real rest.
Walk with me
and work with me.
Watch how I do it.
This is discipleship.
This is apprenticeship.
Learn the unforced
rhythms of grace.
I won't lay anything
heavy or ill-fitting on you.
Keep company with me
and you'll learn
to live freely
and lightly.
Throughout this series,
we've looked at a bunch
of different passages
on prayer,
none more well-known
than Christ's invitation
to ask
and it will be given,
to seek
and you will find,
to knock
and the door
will be opened.
But there's another passage
about knocking,
about approaching God.
The script is flipped
in this passage.
Jesus says to one
of the first century churches
in Revelation,
look,
I stand at the door
and knock.
If you hear my voice
and you open the door,
I will come in
and we will share
a meal together
as friends.
This,
those of you
that are not yet followers
of Jesus,
this is your invitation.
And those of us
that are followers
of Jesus,
this is our daily invitation
to contemplative prayer.
Jesus is standing
at the door
and knocking.
Will you make space
for him?
Will you invite him in?
It's not a religious
requirement
that you don't have to do
or that you have to do
in order to be
on Team Jesus.
It's the loving invitation
of a friend.
Following Jesus
isn't about
religious duty.
The way of Jesus
isn't a long list
of rules
that you have to follow
or you'll get punished.
Jesus extends
both invitations
and warnings.
There's a wide road
and there's an arrow road.
It's up to you
to decide
what you will do
with him.
What will we do
with Christ's invitation
to get away
to a lonely place
to be with him
to rest a while?
Love what Tyler
Staton says.
He says,
prayer in any form
by anybody
is God's invitation
to pull up a chair
to the table
and enjoy restful,
intimate,
unbroken conversation
with the triune God
or as Jesus
succinctly said it,
knock
and the door
will be open
to you.
No matter
where you're at
with you,
your spiritual journey
this morning,
I believe this is
your invitation.
Jesus is knocking.
Will you let him in?
Let's pray.
Father,
I thank you
for your invitation.
that you are
a God of invitation.
You're constantly,
constantly making
invitations
that lead us
to abundant life.
And we are constantly
and constantly
making decisions
that lead us
down a path
of destruction.
And you are
constantly,
constantly
forgiving us,
putting your hand
down
to pull us
back up
and re-inviting us
into your presence
to experience
your love.
God,
today,
wherever we're at
in our spiritual journey,
may we hear
that invitation.
May we receive it
with gladness.
May we create space
in our life
to pause,
to surrender,
to contemplate,
to receive.
It's in Jesus' name
I pray.
Amen.
As I was preparing
this week,
there's a song
that she's got it.
Never mind.
Mic's on.
It's Marissa's mic.
So,
while they work
on getting my mic on,
I would be remiss
if I didn't use
this time
to let us
just practice
this a little bit.
So,
I was going
to sing
one song
and have you
sing it with me,
but tech team,
there we go.
I am not
going to be doing
knowing you,
so you can just
leave the screen
blank
so there is
less distraction.
And if we could
just take some
space
to practice
what Ryan
just said,
like he said,
if this doesn't
serve you
going forward,
maybe not,
but maybe just
try it for today.
I'm going to be
singing a different
song in the
background.
Do not sing
with me.
Just kind of
let it wash
over you
and let's just
take some time
and be with
the Lord
today.
Are you
burnt out
on religious
things?
Are you
worn down
lacking
inner peace
take a real
rest
and walk
along with
me
in the
pastures
of my
presence?
You can
be yourself
and you
can say
what's on
your heart.
I already
know it
all.
Doesn't
matter
what you
say.
Come
and get
away
with
me.
I know
where you
are,
where you've
been and
what you've
seen.
Doesn't
matter how
you come,
come and
get away
with me.
Get away,
get away
with me.
love you.
Are you
are you
burdened
from all
the heavy
days?
It's not
your job
to shoulder
all the weight.
Let me
do it.
come and
take
the lies
you've been
believing in.
the truth
The truth
is that
you have
a place
to say
what's
on your
heart.
I already
know it
all.
Doesn't
matter
what you
say.
Come
and get
away
with me.
I know
where you
are,
where you've
been and
what you've
seen.
doesn't
matter
how you
come.
Come
and get
away
with me.
Get
away,
get away
with me.
So
grace
upon
grace,
let it
lead.
Get
away,
get
away
with me.
Grace
upon
grace,
let it
lead.
Get
away,
get
away
with
me.
Grace
upon
grace,
let it
lead.
Get
away,
get
away
with
me.
Oh,
when
grace,
upon
let you
lead.
Get
away,
get
away
with
me.
And say
what's
on
your
heart.
I
already
know
it
all.
Doesn't
matter
what
you
say,
come
and get
away
with
me.
I
know
where
you
are,
where
you've
been
and what
you've
seen.
Doesn't
matter
how
you
come,
come
and get
away
with
me.
Get
away,
get
away
with
me.
Oh,
and get
away,
get
away
with
me.
Church,
you can
go in
peace,
but I'll
stay and
pray for
anyone that
just wants
to sit
longer
with
the
Lord.
God,